Zeyang Sun, Ph.D.

Department of Geology and Geophysics, Texas A&M University, TX 77843, USA

1 (979) 422-1829 | 2 zeyang.sun@tamu.edu | 0 0000-0002-4187-3532 | 3 github.com/ZSunEPS

RESEARCH INTERESTS

 \mathbf{I} am deeply interested in a range of scientific disciplines, including clumped isotopes, paleoclimate, mass extinctions, terrestrial environments, and carbonate preservation and diagenesis. My long-term research goal is to examine geochemical proxies and the co-evolution of environment and ecology throughout Earth's history.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Geology	Department of Geology and Geophysics, Texas A&M University		2017-2024
	Dissertation:	Carbonate Clumped Isotope Reordering from an Atomic Approach:	
		Heating Experiment, Kinetic Modeling, and Application	
	Advisor:	Ethan Grossman	
B.S., Geology	School of Earth Sciences and Engineering, Nanjing University 2013-		2013–2017
(Hons)	Thesis:	Geochemical Features of Carbonates from Gaoyuzhuang Formation	
,		and Tieling Formation of North China: Implications for the Redox	
		Conditions of Paleo-Ocean	
	Advisor:	Hong-Fei Lin	

Noah Planavsky, Xiangli Wang (Co-advisor)

Professional Experience

Graduate Assistant Researcher in Clumped Isotope Geochemistry	2017-2024
Department of Geology and Geophysics, Texas A&M University	
Advisors: Ethan Grossman, William Defliese (Co-advisor, 2017-2019)	
Research Internship in Metal Isotope Geochemistry	
Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences, Yale University	

PUBLICATIONS (*DENOTES EQUAL CONTRIBUTION)

Advisors:

Accepted & Published

- [3] **Sun, Z.***, Perez-Beltran, S.*, Zaheer, W.*, Defliese, W. F., Banerjee, S., and Grossman, E. L.: Clumped isotope reordering kinetics in strontianite and witherite: experiments and first-principles simulations, *Earth and Planetry Science Letters* 624, p. 118467, 2023. **DOI**: 10.1016/j.epsl.2023.118467.
- [2] Perez-Beltran, S.*, Zaheer, W.*, **Sun, Z.***, Defliese, W. F., Banerjee, S., and Grossman, E. L.: Density functional theory and ab initio molecular dynamics reveal atomistic mechanisms for carbonate clumped isotope reordering, *Science Advances* 9, eadf1701, 2023. **DOI**: 10.1126/sciadv.adf1701.
- [1] **Sun, Z.**, Wang, X., and Planavsky, N.: Cr isotope systematics in the Connecticut River estuary, *Chemical Geology* 506, pp. 29–39, 2019. **DOI**: 10.1016/j.chemgeo.2018.12.034.

Presentations

Conference Submissions

- [7] **Sun, Z.**, Perez-Beltran, S., Defliese, W. F., Banerjee, S., and Grossman, E. L.: Reassessment of calcite clumped isotope preservation using water-facilitated clumped isotope resetting, Oral, in: *Goldschmidt*, Chicago, IL, USA, Aug. 2024.
- [6] Sun, Z., Perez-Beltran, S., Defliese, W. F., Banerjee, S., and Grossman, E. L.: Revisiting clumped isotope resetting in calcites with internal water and organic matter, Oral, in: *International Clumped Isotope Workshop*, Long Island, NY, USA, Aug. 2024.
- [5] **Sun, Z.**, Maupin, C. R., Perez-Beltran, S., Zaheer, W., Defliese, W. F., Banerjee, S., and Grossman, E. L.: The role of internal water in carbonate clumped isotope resetting, Oral, in: *GSA Connects 2023 Meeting*, Pittsburgh, PA, USA, Oct. 2023.
- [4] **Sun, Z.**, Defliese, W. F., and Grossman, E. L.: The kinetics of clumped isotope reordering of synthetic inorganic carbonates, Poster, in: *AGU Fall Meeting*, New Orleans LA, USA, Dec. 2021.

Last update: 11/17/24 Zeyang Sun, Page 1 of 3

CURRICULUM VITAE

- [3] Sun, Z., Defliese, W. F., and Grossman, E. L.: The kinetics of clumped isotope reordering of synthetic inorganic carbonates, Poster, in: GSA Connects 2021 Meeting, Portland, OR, USA, Oct. 2021.
- [2] Sun, Z., Defliese, W. F., and Grossman, E. L.: The kinetics of clumped isotope reordering of synthetic inorganic carbonates, Flash Talk, in: Goldschmidt, Lyon, France (Virtual), July 2021.
- [1] Sun, Z., Defliese, W. F., and Grossman, E. L.: Reconstructing thermal histories of the Oklahoma, Illinois and Moscow basins using clumped isotopes of mid-Carboniferous brachiopods, Poster, in: International Clumped Isotope Workshop, Los Angeles, CA, USA, Jan. 2019.

Honors and Awards

[6]	Student Research Award (2 nd Place) Geology and Geophysics Graduate Society Symposium, TAMU	2024
[5]	ConocoPhillips/HEEP Endowed Graduate Fellowship Department of Geology and Geophysics, TAMU	2022
[4]	Petroleum and Sedimentary Systems Scholarship, Berg-Hughes Center, TAMU	2018
[3]	Honor of Outstanding Graduate, Nanjing University (NJU)	2017
[2]	Pandeng Earth Sciences Scholarship NJU and Institute of Geology and Geophysics, Chinese Academy of Sciences	2015
[1]	Qihang Earth Sciences Scholarship, School of Earth Sciences and Engineering, NJU	2014

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant

[2] Preparing lab session materials, explaining the principle of the IRMS and the carbonate device, and training students to perform carbonate clumped isotope analysis.

Course: GEOL 648 Stable Isotope Geology (Spring 2024 and 2022, Fall 2018), TAMU

Clumped Isotopes of Modern Benthic Foraminifera (Spring 2024) Project:

[1] Preparing class materials, addressing questions, guiding experimental design and instrument use, and tutoring data analysis and visualization with Julia language.

GEOL 450 Geology Senior Project & GEOS 405 Environmental Geosciences (Spring Course:

2023), TAMU

Project: Impact of Gas Stove Usage on Indoor Air Quality and Health

Professional Experience, Engagement and Activities

Reviewer	[1] Science Advances (1), Chemical Geology (1), Palaeo3 (1)	2024
Field Trips	[2] Permian Reef Complex and Guadalupe Mountain, USA	2018
	[1] Late Ordovician Outcrops, Cincinnati Arch Region, USA	2018
Outreach	[4] Geology and Geophysics Undergraduate Summer School, TAMU "How to give an oral presentation and academic conference experiences"	2024
	[3] Chemistry Open House for students, kids, and families "Thermometer in the shell"	2019, 2018
	[2] Ions@WORK Mass Spectrometry Symposium	2018
	[1] Mass Spectrometry for Isotopic Analysis Subunit Open House	2018
Skills		

Instrument **Techniques**

Including operation, troubleshooting, maintenance, and training

- [1] Thermo Scientific[™] 253Plus IRMS
- [2] Thermo Scientific™ Kiel IV Carbonate Device with customized PPQ Trap

Last update: 11/17/24 Zeyang Sun, Page 2 of 3

CURRICULUM VITAE

- [3] Field Emission SEM, CL Microscopy, FTIR Microscopy
- [4] High Temperature Conversion Elemental Analyzer
- [5] Manual Glass Vacuum Line

Programming

Julia, Python, MATLAB®

DOCTORAL PROGRAM COURSES

[9]	CHEM 648 Principles of Quantum Mechanics	Fall 2019
[8]	OCNG 641 Inorganic Aquatic Geochemistry	Spring 2019
[7]	GEOL 648 Stable Isotope Geology	Fall 2018
[6]	CHEM 621 Chemical Kinetics	Spring 2018
[5]	GEOL 658 Earth Systems Through Deep Time: Global Change, Paleoclimate, and Life	Spring 2018
[4]	OCNG 689 Cenozoic Paleoclimate	Spring 2018
[3]	OCNG 655 Experimental Design and Analysis in Oceanography	Fall 2017
[2]	OCNG 640 Chemical Oceanography	Fall 2017
[1]	GEOL 681 Stable Isotope Methods and Research: Clumped Isotope	Fall 2017

REFEREES

Ethan Grossman | Professor and Michel T. Halbouty Chair

Department of Geology and Geophysics, Texas A&M University

Email: e-grossman@geos.tamu.edu

Phone: +1 (979) 845-0637

Sarbajit Banerjee | Professor and Davidson Chair in Science

Department of Chemistry, Texas A&M University

Email: banerjee@chem.tamu.edu

Phone: +1 (979) 862-3102

Yige Zhang | Professor

Guangzhou Institute of Geochemistry, Chinese Academy of Sciences

Email: zhangyige@gig.ac.cn Phone: +86 (020) 8529-2969

Last update: 11/17/24 Zeyang Sun, Page 3 of 3